THE FROZEN DEAD
Captain Servaz?
Yeah?
Hi, I'm Captain Ziegler,
head of the St. Martin detective squad.
Have you been briefed?
Not really.
Come, I'll show you.
May I?
It's up to you.
Do you know the area?
Yes, I do.
That's enough!
You can't take it?
Thanks for coming
so soon, Martin.
Madam prosecutor.
That's the surprise?
I'm no good at presents.
-Can I borrow him for 2 minutes?
-Of course.
I'm sure it's a pain coming
all this way for a horse.
But I've got pressure from above.
Because of a horse?
No.
Because of the owner,
a certain Eric Lombard.
That animal was worth 600,000
and he owns one of the
biggest factories in the region.
He's not yet 40 but he's head
of a listed company.
Cathy, I'd rather you put
someone else on this job.
I don't want to get back into politics,
and I've got 3 homeless murdered
in Toulouse.
You know shit always rolls downhill.
It's very clear they want you
on the team.
There's nobody else?
Lombard knows powerful people.
They see you as a good detective.
Even if you don't believe that now.
Please Cathy, I don't want to be here.
Please.
Martin...
I don't want to tell them
you've refused.
Just an expert consultation
to start the investigation.
Two days, then I'm leaving.
It's good that you're here.
All the Intervention Brigade guys
are on a big drugs case.
We're not really used to twisted stuff.
I'm only here to give you a hand.
It's your case, Captain.
Aren't we too formal?
If you think so.
Listen, I don't understand...
You found the corpse at 7am.
Why did you only call
the police at 7.30?
I had to go down to find a signal.
OK.
So you discovered this thing,
you tried to call using
your mobile phone.
It didn't work, so you left.
-Correct.
-Why didn't you use the factory phone?
Dammit, I told you it wasn't us.
Find the sicko who did it
instead of hassling us.
Sit down.
May I?
Could you stand up?
She told me to sit down.
Get up.
How much will I find
in your locker?
Louder, I can't hear you.
The cold mornings are tough.
Sometimes we smoke a little joint.
That's why you hesitated
to call?
Go on, get out.
Get lost, I said.
Could you explain?
Can you explain?
To be quick and effective,
you must prioritise.
That guy isn't a priority.
How did it get up here?
We searched the cabin
but found nothing.
Where's the head?
Is there another way to get here
besides the cable car?
Yes.
There's a little road
behind the factory.
Shall we go and have a look?
Of course.
You should wear a parka.
Yeah.
-Where does this road go?
-Into the valley.
The Lombards own all this.
Well, Eric Lombard...
His parents are dead.
When did the son take over
the business?
Six months ago.
Not everyone's happy with it.
Why not?
The father knew his company
was important to the local economy,
and made sure everyone benefited.
It's not the same with his son.
He wants to clean up
"polluting regional industries"...
Not a bad idea.
No, but lots of people don't like it.
What the hell's that?
Got a torch?
Yes.
Here.
WARNIER PSYCHIATRIC UNIT
Trying to punish yourself again?
I can't be punished.
Why not?
When you're punished,
you start again.
And you can't start again?
You mean that nothing
can forgive your crime?
I had a dream last night.
A dream I hadn't had for years.
I dreamt...
I was cutting up my mother.
But everyone dreams, Francis.
-You don't have to...
-I won't be punished!
And your first victim...
Was he a priest, Francis?
Why him?
Why a priest?
Did you know him?
-Dr Ferney?
-Yes, Francis.
Tell her not to ask me again, please.
Dr Berg, let's leave Francis to rest.
Right, Francis?
He refused to absolve your sins,
didn't he?
He'll never forgive me.
Who?
Who will never forgive you, Francis?
God?
It's secured.
They're waiting.
OK, I'll send 2 guys immediately.
Is this his head?
Same colour.
Same mark. Seems likely.
We found this in the blood.
-What? A hair?
-Perhaps.
This is huge.
What have you got?
Not much.
He wasn't killed here.
Would a horse like that follow
a stranger without making a fuss?
That's what I wonder.
We started looking for
prints of feet, hooves, tyres...
But in such a busy place...
I've gathered the staff
so you can question them.
-Is Mr Lombard here?
-No, he's in London.
He'll be here as soon as he can.
Freedom was his favourite.
-Mr Lombard is very sad...
-Who used to ride this horse?
Nobody except Mr Lombard and Ben.
Ben?
Ben McFinley, the man
who looks after the horses.
Is he here?
No. He's not feeling well,
he didn't want to join us.
Where can we find him?
-Mr McFinley?
-Yes?
Captain Servaz, from CRPJ Toulouse.
I've got a few questions about Freedom.
Go ahead.
When did you last see him?
Yesterday at 8.
-Where were you last night?
-I was out with a woman.
So she can confirm that?
I don't know, she's married.
Mr McFinley, could you get down
so we can talk properly?
Stop!
Aren't you on duty in Block C?
No, they're in activities now.
Already? Shit, I'm late.
You did well earlier with Imbert.
I mean it.
It's great he tolerated you so quickly,
but what you made him say... Wow!
So can I see the detainees in Block A?
That again?
You don't give up.
Don't worry, you'll be allowed.
But you've only been here 15 days
and even I had to wait several weeks.
-Elisabeth! We must work on the budget.
-Can't it wait?
No, it can't.
We'll talk about it later.
You're a killjoy, François!
I know, your patients
over my accounting.
Who knows what's logical...
If for whatever reason he really
held a grudge against his boss,
he'd attack him directly.
That guy really loves horses,
he wouldn't commit such butchery.
He did try to escape,
and he was armed.
When will they let you see him?
Excuse me, your room is ready.
Thanks.
I know I promised,
but I want to leave tonight.
What? You've got an interesting suspect,
a DNA analysis underway.
Ziegler's great,
she'll be fine on her own.
I'm going back to Toulouse,
I've got too much work there.
It's funny, I thought you'd
ask me if you could stay longer.
Let me go Cathy,
you know I'm tired.
He's been locked up for 10 years.
Thanks to you, he'll never be free.
He killed 6 people before I realised.
Martin, Hirtmann tricked everyone,
not only you.
He was my daughter's godfather, Cathy.
How about me? He was my colleague
for almost 12 years.
I had lunch with him almost every day,
I saw him more than my husband.
We really were fooled, weren't we.
Pull yourself together.
You should
have been promoted years ago.
Draw a line under it
and move on.
Let me go Cathy.
Please.
You know, I've just understood.
For all these years,
I thought you felt guilty,
but actually you're afraid.
You're letting your fear take over,
Martin.
How much is that?
Hirtmann?
More origami?
It relaxes me, my friend.
Thanks.
She loved the elephant.
I used to sculpt.
Bring me wood and a knife,
and I'll make her a unicorn.
A knife? Really?
I guess that's a 'no'.
How are you? Not too cold?
How could I be cold after
those winters in Quebec?
And how's your work?
You look tired.
Are they very difficult?
Mum, they're disabled,
they're not aliens.
Don't put words in my mouth.
But the other day, I saw a documentary
about a re-education centre like yours
and it looked tough, that's all.
Well yeah it's tough,
but it's worse for them.
I miss you, darling.
I'd have loved to have Christmas
with you.
Yeah, me too.
Mum, I need to go.
I'll call you later.
Good night.
Yes?
Are you OK?
I heard a noise.
It's nothing, it's just my mirror...
-Shit.
-Show me.
No, no, it's fine, really.
-No, but it's nothing.
-Don't worry, I'll clean it...
-No, leave it Alex!
-Where's the antiseptic?
-I don't think I've got any.
It's OK, I've found it.
Sit down.
Hey, it's the first time
I've been in your room.
I hoped it'd be different.
You're being a pain.
OK. Did you feel it stinging?
-Here you are, miss.
-Thanks.
Want to tell me what happened?
Go on. I saw you
walk past the canteen.
You looked really angry.
No, it's Ferney.
She still won't let me
work with Block A patients.
Are they so different?
No, not really.
But it's you who has the files.
I'd like to be a mouse to observe them.
Who'd you visit first?
-Hirtmann?
-What do you think?
Of course.
-Is he so scary?
-No.
It's weird to think
he killed those girls.
-Can I ask you a favour?
-Yes.
My badge won't let me access Block A.
So I wanted to know...
if you'd lend me yours.
-You're not serious, Diane.
-It's just to see them.
You're crazy,
you want to get us fired?
Servaz.
It's Irene. We've found a snow plough
covered in blood and hair.
It could be from our horse.
-Where are you?
-Downstairs.
You left me alone last night.
I won't sleep here
while he's here.
Why not?
I work with him,
I don't want him seeing me in PJs.
There's always an excuse.
Morning.
-Shall we go?
-Let's go.
Bye.
Where's this snow plough?
Outside,
I came here in it.
The Forensic Team is taking care of it.
We're going straight to the owner's,
is that OK?
As long as we don't go in PJs.
What about the hair?
OK. Thanks Lucas,
call me when you know.
So?
No human traces this time. They found
animal blood and hair from Freedom.
Morning captain. Your guys warned me.
Come on in.
No, usually I'm at the garage.
Someone else takes care of the shop,
but her son's ill so
I'm working in the shop.
Is it just you at the garage
and vehicle hire?
My employee and apprentice
are on holiday this week.
That's why I was late
reporting the theft.
Have you seen
anything unusual?
No...
And I pay attention.
I've had a snowmobile stolen,
but I didn't expect a snow plough.
And then they used it for...
Well if you recall anything,
let us know.
That's just what you need.
It's from last year.
I'll give you a discount.
What? Do I look like a pumpkin?
No, more like a carrot.
Yeah, you enjoy mocking me.
You OK?
You must think I'm pathetic.
No, I've seen worse.
I never got used to the smell.
It would be odd if you did.
We already know
he died of a heart attack
due to an overdose of anaesthetics
or poison such as curare.
The decapitation occurred post mortem,
and given the state of the skin
and flesh, most likely with a chainsaw.
He was then butchered with
a hunter's or butcher's knife.
So anyone could have done it?
Yes. Any hunter accustomed
to butchering a wild boar or deer.
I'll be back.
No, darling, it'll be fine, I promise.
Eat with your mum tonight.
That'll make me happy, OK?
What are you going to do?
Stop worrying about me,
I'm your father not your son.
I'm going to Vincent and Charlene's.
I won't be alone.
OK then.
I called the office and Vincent said
you were in Comminges.
Why didn't you say?
Because I'll be back this evening.
-OK with you?
-Where are you exactly?
In St. Martin.
Because of him?
Of course not.
A horse was killed and as the owner's
a millionaire or billionaire,
we have to find the guy who
wanted to make lasagne.
-Not funny, Dad.
-I know.
Captain Servaz?
Got to go, sweetie.
-Call me this evening.
-I promise.
Raphaël Delaunay, local reporter
at the Courier.
I knew it wouldn't be long
before you showed up.
Better a decapitated horse
than a run-over dog, eh?
I'm happier to cover a case led by
the policeman who caught Hirtmann.
Check your information.
The case is led by Captain Ziegler.
Why are you here then?
Because he did military service
in the cavalry. Will that do?
Come on Raphaël, do us
a favour and let us work.
One question, Captain.
What's it like
being so close to Julian Hirtmann?
Goodbye.
The hospital called. McFinley's better.
We can question him.
Where's the guard?
Shit.
-McFinley?
-Wait.
-Captain!
-Where were you?
A doctor said there was
a brawl downstairs.
It was only 5 minutes.
No, no, don't move.
Bring him to me immediately
if he shows up, OK?
Nothing at Lombard's.
Well, we're sure the groom
is involved now.
Right, I'm off.
Go meet your daughter.
Send the report in two days.
I take you to the hostel.
-Happy Christmas.
-But it's yours!
Take it.
Well, it's goodbye then.
Go on.
Go on, you'll do great.
Happy Christmas.
Bye.
Francis Imbert was tortured
by his father,
always in front of his mother.
He needed a witness.
And as it was her who was tortured
before her son was born,
the poor woman let Francis
be abused instead.
I don't remember
seeing that in his file.
No, he only told me earlier.
But it's due to you, Diane.
You freed him from something.
-Aren't you going to ask?
-What?
To work with the patients in Block A.
You've been asking since the start.
You mean you accept?
I think it's time.
Thanks.
Go on.
-Happy Christmas!
-Happy Christmas.
Very funny. It's lucky
some of us work, eh?
We're slackers, is that right?
A load of slackers.
Tell him, Vince.
Tell me what?
-We caught the murderers.
-No way.
-This afternoon.
-They're in custody?
You should have seen how
we screwed them.
It's you who'd have got screwed
if we hadn't been there!
Want to see them?
If you want to be Captain one day
you must understand...
you caught them, you deal with them!
Thank you Lord.
Is the boss in?
He's just left, he's cooking tonight.
Right then... Happy Christmas
you bunch of slackers!
Happy Christmas, Martin!
Martin! Where are you off to?
To see my daughter.
Maud called. She asked if
I'd really invited you round.
-What did you say?
-What do you think?
I'm tired. I didn't want to say
I was spending Christmas Eve in bed.
And why lie to me?
Because I don't want your pity either.
OK, come and have dinner with us.
We've got enough food for a year.
Vincent...
Small ball... Number 11.
Oh yes!
Number 12... A 12?
12? No 12?
It turns again, it turns...
-What fun!
-Yeah!
73! 73? 73?
-73! Pierre! Come get your prize!
-Great Christmas Eve, huh?
Two years of this.
Let's check first.
I want to have kids
so I get holidays off.
It's your lucky day!
Show me.
I need a fag or I'll go mad.
You coming?
How great!
Bravo Pierre, happy Christmas!
Happy Christmas, Pierre!
-We haven't clapped for Pierre!
-Let's clap nice and loud!
Pierre, happy Christmas!
-Shall we continue?
-Let's!
-Why did you come to work here?
-How so?
I don't know. You come from Montreal,
you don't know anyone in the region.
All to spend time with guys who
make Jack the Ripper look cute.
So why are you here?
Hey, you've been answering my questions
with another question since you arrived.
What do you want me to say?
I was fed up with Canada.
And to answer,
you don't hesitate when given the chance
to work at a centre like Warnier.
So why do you work here?
Around here there's not much choice.
Old people, or psychiatrics.
I was sick
of dealing with old people.
I'm going inside, I'm freezing.
Have you finished?
What's your problem, Diane?
If you don't fancy me, why flirt?
You're allowed to look.
She's beautiful.
Fuck! Is it me
or is the room spinning?
I've drunk too much too,
I'm going to head off.
Bye, old man.
Thanks.
Yeah, happy Christmas.
Martin?
Why did you come?
He invited me.
I know I shouldn't have come.
I won't anymore.
I'm pregnant.
Since when?
Since the last time.
3 months ago.
Does Vincent know?
What will you do?
Martin, it's his child.
Not yours.
You hear me?
Be careful driving home.
Martin?
Irene.
The hair we found by the horse's head...
It's Hirtmann's.
Martin?
I'll call you back.